<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>silky.github.io</title>
    <link href="https://silky.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://silky.github.io" />
    <id>https://silky.github.io/atom.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Noon van der Silk</name>
        <email>noonsilk+-noonsilk@gmail.com</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2021-06-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>☐ He died with a todo list in his hand ...</title>
    <link href="https://silky.github.io/posts/died-todo-list.html" />
    <id>https://silky.github.io/posts/died-todo-list.html</id>
    <published>2021-06-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-06-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on June  3, 2021
    
        by Noon van der Silk
    
</div>

<center>
<img width="600" src="/images/todo-list.png"/> <br /> <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0172543/">A classic Australian movie</a>: A nightmare chase through hell in a never-ending, unrequited daisy chain of desire… .
</center>
<p>What is time? How do we measure a life? How many things did you get done today? What are you working on tomorrow!? Can you come hang out on Sunday!!?</p>
<hr />
<p>Recently, and also always, I’ve been thinking about how to manage a list of todos. During an internal knowledge-sharing session <a href="https://www.tweag.io/">at work</a> I was prompted to reflect on all the different schemes I’ve tried:</p>
<ul>
<li>Random pieces of paper</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_Notepad">Notepad</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fZj0WLxj-T0">Windows sticky notes</a></li>
<li><a href="https://tiddlywiki.com/">Tiddlywiki</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/MediaWiki">Mediawiki</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jira_(software)">Jira</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.vim.org/">Vim</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/romainl/vim-qf">Vim quickfix window</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/silky/utils/tree/master/find-todo">A terrible custom python script</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/vimwiki/vimwiki">Vimwiki</a></li>
<li>Text files</li>
<li><a href="https://orgmode.org/">Org-Mode</a> (I gave up almost immediately)</li>
<li>Emails to myself</li>
<li>A private mailing list I made up</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique">Pomodoro</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues">Github issues</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trello">Trello</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.notion.so/">Notion</a></li>
<li><a href="https://asana.com/">Asana</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/README">Readme files</a></li>
<li><a href="https://taskwarrior.org/">Taskwarrior</a></li>
<li><a href="https://bulletjournal.com/pages/learn">Bullet journal</a> (for &lt;4 minutes)</li>
<li>Physical notebooks</li>
<li>Fancy notebooks</li>
<li>Cheap notebooks</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kanban_board">Physical ‘kanban’ cards</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/silky/ideas#complete">A whiteboard</a></li>
<li>My head</li>
<li>Nothing</li>
<li>Random pieces of paper</li>
</ul>
<p>Right now I’m back to a whiteboard (by luck I happen to have one behind me where I work), and ‘todo’ notes in code + github issues.</p>
<p>But that’s irrelevant. Or is it?!</p>
<p>My friend Ruth told me something that perhaps is very obvious but was also surprisingly calming to me: You’ll die with items on your todo list. So don’t worry about it!</p>
<p>I think there’s a few ways to think about this:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The optimisic view: Amazing that I be lucky enough to have things I intend to do and look forward to!</li>
<li>The pessimistic view: Sad that I had goals that I was never able to achieve!</li>
<li>The Buddhist view: Your big mistake is having desires at all!</li>
</ol>
<p>I want to live around option (3) and (1) at the moment, but of course option (2) is a very very strong driving force; and often necessary (for example, at work!); the only time I was brave enough to enact option (3) at a work setting was when <a href="https://braneshop.com.au/posts/Braneshop-A-Living-Business-Part-1.html">I ran my own business</a>!</p>
<p>Another interesting thing that came up as part of the work discussion was that in some ways what you want to do depends on your mood. No doubt! So … maybe mood can be a parameter?!</p>
<hr />
<p>I think, secretly, for the rest of my life, I will believe that there is a True answer out there; an ultimate organisation scheme; the Four-Fold path to Life Efficiency: Right Editing, Right Organisation, Right Workflow and Right History.</p>
<p>But I also think that I should never think about this again. But on the other hand, I was inspired at the talk today; so I might give task-warrior another go.</p>
<p>But, you didn’t come here for that! Maybe you came here for advice? So, here it is (it’s not even my advice! Gala claims it’s her idea which is probably true):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you can, don’t even write the thing down; just do it immediately, or, alternatively, convince yourself you don’t need to think about it now.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Maybe it’s part of my personality, but this works <em>surprisingly</em> well for me. Especially if it’s something that I’m working on with someone else; instead of delaying my part, I can just try and make as much progress as I can immediately, and send it back to the other person! Another way of saying this: I can offset storing my todo list to you!</p>
<p>I find this idea to be quite operaitonal; I often find myself using this rule to do something sooner rather than later.</p>
<p>Here’s one thing I know about myself: <a href="https://scirate.com/noonsilk">I can’t be trusted with lists</a>. I get a bit obsessed with organising them. So I’m trying to avoid them these days.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>2020 Books</title>
    <link href="https://silky.github.io/posts/2020-books.html" />
    <id>https://silky.github.io/posts/2020-books.html</id>
    <published>2021-02-14T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-02-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on February 14, 2021
    
        by Noon van der Silk
    
</div>

<style type="text/css">
div.book {
 display:        flex;
 flex-direction: row;
 padding:        10px;
}

div.book img { margin-right: 10px; width: 150px; }

div.alt { background: #eaeaea; }
</style>
<p>Continuing the tradition <a href="/posts/2019-01-03-2018-books.html">started in 2018</a>, continued in 2019 <a href="https://braneshop.com.au/posts/2019-Books.html">over on the Braneshop blog</a>, I was reminded I haven’t posted the books I read in 2020 yet.</p>
<p>So, here we are:</p>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/how-long-til-black-future-month.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/40855636-how-long-til-black-future-month">How Long ’til Black Future Month?</a></strong> by Jemisin, N.K.</p>
<p>As a big fan of N.K. Jemisin I just wanted to read more of what she’d written. This is good for that; it’s a really nice dip-in to the worlds she has created and leaves you wanting more!</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/gravitys-century.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/40010687-gravity-s-century">Gravity’s Century: From Einstein’s Eclipse to Images of Black Holes</a></strong> by Cowen, Ron</p>
<p>Pretty good. This was a nice history of black holes and an introduction to some of the pressing issues presently.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/the-cloudspotters-guide.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/174372.The_Cloudspotter_s_Guide">The Cloudspotter’s Guide</a></strong> by Pretor-Pinney, Gavin</p>
<p>I picked this up after starting (but not finishing) <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/8474155-the-wavewatcher-s-companion">The Wavewatcher’s Companion</a>, which I found to be hilarious. This book was not as funny, but was still pretty good. Gavin has a very nice way of appreciating the world.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/altruism.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/22208239-altruism">Altruism: The Power of Compassion to Change Yourself and the World</a></strong> by Ricard, Matthieu</p>
<p>I really quite enjoyed this book, and infact wrote a longer review over on the <a href="https://betweenbooks.com.au/reviews/2020/altruism-matthieu-ricard-2015.html">Between Books</a> website.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/girl-woman-other.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/41081373-girl-woman-other">Girl, Woman, Other</a></strong> by Evaristo, Bernardine</p>
<p>A nice collection of stories featuring different women and how their lives intersect. I think it’s quite nice to get so many stories from the everyday lives of women; especially for me, for whom it’s a bit unknown territory.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/the-white-album.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/421.The_White_Album">The White Album</a></strong> by Didion, Joan</p>
<p>The first Joan Didion book I’ve read. She’s very famous of course; and I don’t know. It was good to read; but was it objectionably good? Maybe. It’s at least nice to know a bit about her life and how she writes. I’ll probably read more.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/mullumbimby.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/17319691-mullumbimby">Mullumbimby</a></strong> by Lucashenko, Melissa</p>
<p>I quite enjoyed this story. It’s also the first time I’ve read a modern fictional Australian indigenous-centered story. Will be on the look out for more books of this kind! Came up as part of the <a href="https://ochouse.com.au/">OC House</a> bookclub, I think.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/down-girl.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/34640834-down-girl">Down Girl: The Logic of Misogyny</a></strong> by Manne, Kate</p>
<p>This book is amazing. I found it to be written in a bit of an academic-y style; so it can be a bit dense, but it does an amazing job of framing what misogyny is and how it is present in all aspects of society.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/unfree-speech.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/49964359-unfree-speech">Unfree Speech: The Threat to Global Democracy and Why We Must Act, Now</a></strong> by Wong, Joshua</p>
<p>This is a nice short history of free speech and how China is taking over Hong Kong. It was interesting to read about how they attempted to make some large changes to their democracy through grass-roots organisation. In some ways quite inspiring, but also a reality check that it isn’t easy to defeat power. Worth a read.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/a-month-in-siena.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/43783430-a-month-in-siena">A Month in Siena</a></strong> by Matar, Hisham</p>
<p>This was just a nice simple book about someone getting amongst life in a new town. In many ways I think this kind of experience is how many people wish their holidays to go: meeting some nice stranger, integrating into the community, and just appreciating the joy of life.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/the-weil-conjectures.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/41940441-the-weil-conjectures">The Weil Conjectures: On Math and the Pursuit of the Unknown</a></strong> by Olsson, Karen</p>
<p>I can’t remember much about this book at this point; I think I enjoyed it.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/the-worst-journey-in-the-world.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/48503.The_Worst_Journey_in_the_World">The Worst Journey in the World</a></strong> by Cherry-Garrard, Apsley</p>
<p>I read the next two books back-to-back. This one was strange. It’s written from the English perspective; it’s quite racist at times. I wouldn’t recommend reading it, unless you really want to compare perspectives on the journeys of Scott and Amundsen.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/the-last-place-on-earth.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/549488.The_Last_Place_on_Earth">The Last Place on Earth: Scott and Amundsen’s Race to the South Pole</a></strong> by Huntford, Roland</p>
<p>This was a really interesting read. It was so fascinating to compare how Amundsen approached the journey compared to Scott. According to this book, Scott was woefully underprepared and arrogant, and Amundsen spent many many years training and learning the right skills from different indigenous groups in order to survive.</p>
<p>If you want to learn about the race to the south pole; this book is definitely better than the above.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/food-rules.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/7015635-food-rules">Food Rules: An Eater’s Manual</a></strong> by Pollan, Michael</p>
<p>More of a blog post than a book; but still, nice to keep next to you somewhere when you want to remember if it’s okay to eat chocolate everyday (probably not) or have a wine with dinner (probably fine).</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/men-explain-things-to-me.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/18528190-men-explain-things-to-me">Men Explain Things to Me</a></strong> by Solnit, Rebecca</p>
<p>Hilarious. This is a collection of stories; some funnier than others, but overall great.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/the-shadow-of-the-sun.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/9541.The_Shadow_of_the_Sun">The Shadow of the Sun</a></strong> by Kapuściński, Ryszard</p>
<p>I enjoyed this as a nice way to get a bit of, albeit an outsiders, insight into how different people live in some of the poorer parts of Africa.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/capital-and-ideology.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/50849430-capital-and-ideology">Capital and Ideology</a></strong> by Piketty, Thomas</p>
<p>I really enjoyed this book, and wrote about it more over on <a href="https://betweenbooks.com.au/reviews/2020/capital-and-ideology-thomas-piketty-2020.html">Between Books - Capital and Ideology</a></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/capital-in-the-twenty-first-century.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/18736925-capital-in-the-twenty-first-century">Capital in the Twenty-First Century</a></strong> by Piketty, Thomas</p>
<p>This one I also enjoyed; I don’t think you really need to read it first before Ideology, but I opted to do so. Reading this really inspired a love and interest of economics, and Piketty seems to do an amazing job of exploring these topics in an approachable way.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/affluence-without-abundance.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/31451192-affluence-without-abundance">Affluence Without Abundance: The Disappearing World of the Bushmen</a></strong> by Suzman, James</p>
<p>This book wasn’t bad; it’s an exploration of life with a marginalised tribe referred to as the Bushmen. It doesn’t totally take the expected view that the simple life is better; but it does discuss how politics and the community encroaches on this tribe, and how they live life.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/a-woman-in-the-polar-night.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/8266887-a-woman-in-the-polar-night">A Woman in the Polar Night</a></strong> by Ritter, Christiane</p>
<p>I think this is a classic book; it’s a little strange, but it does show one persons journey into the Arctic and how she learned to love it. It didn’t exactly inspire me to go and life there, but I do admire her approach!</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/touching-the-void.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/18600.Touching_the_Void">Touching the Void: The True Story of One Man’s Miraculous Survival</a></strong> by Simpson, Joe</p>
<p>This is amazing. I read this assuming a particular fact about the story (I won’t spoil it by telling you), but it turned out that my mind was blown by what actually happened. I’ll probably read it again!</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/into-thin-air.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/1898.Into_Thin_Air">Into Thin Air: A Personal Account of the Mount Everest Disaster</a></strong> by Krakauer, Jon</p>
<p>I bought this I think after the one above; desperate for more books about climbing. This is also an amazing story; I think if anything it made me feel certain that I’ll never attempt to climb Everest.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/honjin.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/5863774-the-case-of-the-honjin-murder">The Case of the Honjin Murder</a></strong> by Yokomizo, Seishi</p>
<p>I just happened across this one in the bookshop and thought I’d give it a go. I can’t say it was the best; it was quite sexist. The story was probably pretty good, if you could ignore that; but I couldn’t.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/tall-man.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/3901371-tall-man">Tall Man: The Death of Doomadgee</a></strong> by Hooper, Chloe</p>
<p>This was a good read but super aggravating. It’s really unsettling to learn how terrible some of the policing is; and the subsequent investigations that yielded no useful outcome. Eye-opening for me in terms of how bad racism is in Australia.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/mountains-of-the-mind.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/839157.Mountains_of_the_Mind">Mountains of the Mind: A History of a Fascination</a></strong> by Macfarlane, Robert</p>
<p>Pretty good. I went through a phase of reading about mountain climbing. This was a nice little overview of how people justify climbing. Good for an introduction to other things to read.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/the-city-we-became.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/42074525-the-city-we-became">The City We Became (Great Cities, #1)</a></strong> by Jemisin, N.K.</p>
<p>For how much I loved her other books; I have to say I found this one a bit disappointing. I think by normal sci-fi standards, it’s certainly excellent, and I’ll definitely read the rest of the series; but if you’re looking for something as amazing as her other books, you might not find it here.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/annapurna.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/306659.Annapurna">Annapurna: A Woman’s Place</a></strong> by Blum, Arlene</p>
<p>I really enjoyed this one. It was interesting to compare this to other climbing books written by men, which almost never feature much uncertainty or collaborative leadership.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/underland.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/41817481-underland">Underland: A Deep Time Journey</a></strong> by Macfarlane, Robert</p>
<p>This is just super cool. We are taken on a journey through lots of different underground worlds. Certainly makes you want to do this kind of exploring.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/the-eastern-curlew.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/41011110-the-eastern-curlew">The Eastern Curlew</a></strong> by Saddler, Harry</p>
<p>I read this after meeting the author at a party! I felt so cool; I’d never met an author in real life before. Inspired by that meeting, I picked it up. It’s really a nice story about following the migratory path of a bird, and thinking about how their ecosystem is being impacted. Would definitely recommend!</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/her-body-and-other-parties.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/33375622-her-body-and-other-parties">Her Body and Other Parties</a></strong> by Machado, Carmen Maria</p>
<p>Not bad. Probably not my favourite style of book, but if you like weird kind of magical fiction with a message, probably quite good.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/my-sister-the-serial-killer.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/38819868-my-sister-the-serial-killer">My Sister, the Serial Killer</a></strong> by Braithwaite, Oyinkan</p>
<p>I quite enjoyed this one; it was a very quick read; so I’m looking forward to more by this author!</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/in-praise-of-shadows.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/34473.In_Praise_of_Shadows">In Praise of Shadows</a></strong> by Tanizaki, Jun’ichirō</p>
<p>Pretty good. Very very short; but a thoughtful analysis of how light impacts space. I think it’s a classic of the architecture world.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/barbarian-days.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/18693910-barbarian-days">Barbarian Days: A Surfing Life</a></strong> by Finnegan, William</p>
<p>I really really enjoyed this one. Very nicely written, you feel like you’re living the life alongside the author. It’s nice to read about someone who follows their passion so directly.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/why-im-no-longer-talking-to-white-people-about-race.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/33606119-why-i-m-no-longer-talking-to-white-people-about-race">Why I’m No Longer Talking to White People About Race</a></strong> by Eddo-Lodge, Reni</p>
<p>I picked this up as soon as I arrived in the UK, to gain an understanding for how people here think about race issues. Pretty good reading.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/kon-tiki.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/790171.Kon_Tiki">Kon-Tiki</a></strong> by Heyerdahl, Thor</p>
<p>This was a funny one. A classic kind of adventure story, from real life, I have to say I enjoyed it.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/mad-bad-dangerous-to-know.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/2060190.Mad_Bad_Dangerous_to_Know">Mad, Bad &amp; Dangerous to Know: The Autobiography</a></strong> by Fiennes, Ranulph</p>
<p>I found this one also kind of funny. I suppose this guy is very famous in the UK, but I’d not heard of him really. It’s funny to read about how he thinks of endurance, and his claim that “anyone” can be like him; in terms of running 7 marathons at the age of 70 across 7 countries; or something along those lines. Didn’t exactly encourage me to do the same, but did give me some food for thought about willpower and energy.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/see-what-you-made-me-do.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/43800661-see-what-you-made-me-do">See What You Made Me Do: Power, Control and Domestic Violence</a></strong> by Hill, Jess</p>
<p>This is a very hard book to read, emotionally. It contains some exceptionally difficult stories. Definitely recommended reading, but if you want a more academic treatment see the earlier book by Kate Manne.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/2020-reading/becoming-bodhisattvas.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com//book/show/40669652-becoming-bodhisattvas">Becoming Bodhisattvas</a></strong> by Chödrön, Pema</p>
<p>Easily the best book I read last year. Of course it’s a buddhist view on how to live life; but I found it very practical and thoughtful. I’ve read it again during some difficult times, and found it very uplifting.</p>
</div>
</div>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>New job; moving to Cambridge!</title>
    <link href="https://silky.github.io/posts/melbourne-cambridge.html" />
    <id>https://silky.github.io/posts/melbourne-cambridge.html</id>
    <published>2020-10-12T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-10-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on October 12, 2020
    
        by Noon van der Silk
    
</div>

<p>So, I’m very excited to share that we’re moving overseas! We’re headed to Cambridge in the UK at the end of this month.</p>
<p>I’m very lucky to be starting work with a very cool quantum computing company: <a href="https://www.riverlane.com/">Riverlane</a>.</p>
<h2 id="leaving-melbourne">Leaving Melbourne</h2>
<p>It’s going to be interesting leaving Melbourne. I’ve lived here all my life basically, and I’ve found a really nice group of friends. I’m going to miss everyone.</p>
<p>I owe a big thanks to <strong>everyone</strong> that’s helped me in my career and life over the years here. I won’t list all of you, but thanks :) I wouldn’t be where I am if I hadn’t had your help and support. ❤️ 💖</p>
<p>In particular the meetup community has been a great place for me and somewhere I was able to forge some really strong friendships. Specifically, I’ve had a great time at the Melbourne Maths and Science Meetup, the Haskell Meetup, back in the day I loved MXUG, and of course I have to thank my friend David Kemp for being the only consistent attendee of the Quantum Lunch, started way back in the day! I’ll also miss hanging out with the cool people who’ve come to events I’ve helped organise, such as <a href="https://www.composeconference.org/2016-melbourne/">compose conference</a> and <a href="https://postpredictionconference.github.io/">post-prediction conference</a>. I love Melbourne for the really nice connection you get between different communities, and it’s been some of my favourite times meeting people from outside my standard little bubble.</p>
<p>I also have to thank my friend Charles Hill from Melbourne University, who taught me so much about quantum computing, is an amazing researcher and very kind and generous person.</p>
<p>Thanks also to the other people in the tech community here that have supported me and helped me first move into new jobs and learn interesting and fun things. I’ve been very lucky.</p>
<p>Of course, thanks again to all the people that helped out with <a href="https://braneshop.com.au/">Braneshop</a> whom I’ve already mentioned over there.</p>
<h2 id="cambridge">Cambridge</h2>
<p>We’re totally new to Cambridge, so if you’ve got suggestions/connections I’d love to hear about it! Definitely keen to meet some people and get into the community over there.</p>
<p><strong>Reach out if you like!</strong></p>
<p>I’ve benefited a lot from emailing random people and just asking questions, so please feel free to reach out to me if you think I can help with anything!</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Privileges</title>
    <link href="https://silky.github.io/posts/privileges.html" />
    <id>https://silky.github.io/posts/privileges.html</id>
    <published>2020-10-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-10-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on October  1, 2020
    
        by Noon van der Silk
    
</div>

<p>Inspired by this recent paper - <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2009.14258.pdf">Towards decolonising computational sciences</a> - I thought it might be a nice idea to write down a list of privileges that I can identify I have. I’ll probably update this list as I think of them.</p>
<p>My list:</p>
<ul>
<li>White, Male, Cisgendered: I don’t often feel out of place.</li>
<li>Healthy: Nothing has prevented me from finding work.</li>
<li>Able-bodied: Getting around is easy.</li>
<li>Somewhat extroverted: Able to engage and network somewhat easily when I want to.</li>
<li>No dependants: Freedom to move around and spend time as I wish.</li>
<li>Financial stability from a young age: Able to take (moderate) risks.</li>
<li>Supportive parent: I know I’ll have a place to go.</li>
<li>Supportive partner: Financial/emotional support to experiment.</li>
<li>Live close to the city: Access to events, convenience.</li>
<li>Good mental health: I’m able to focus when I want; am most of the time moderately calm.</li>
<li>Language: I speak English natively.</li>
<li>Exposed to tech from a young age: I had a computer in the house since I was young, and was able to learn programming on my own as a result.</li>
<li>Well-educated: I went to a private school, and was eventually able to attend good universities and get access to experts and knowledge in this way.</li>
</ul>
<p>These things have helped me get jobs in the past. Some of them are traits that you can improve, as well as baseline things thare are out of my control to some degree (i.e. mental health; certainly it can be improved, but certainly it’s not all my doing.)</p>
<p>I also found this: <a href="https://sites.google.com/a/u.boisestate.edu/social-justice-training/about-us/our-training/privilege-checklist">Privilege Checklist</a> from this <a href="https://sites.google.com/a/u.boisestate.edu/social-justice-training/home">Social Justice Training</a> program, that is a very good starting point for building a comprehensive list. This feels like a great exercise for teams to get together and think about.</p>
<p>What’s your list?</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>2018s Crazy Ideas</title>
    <link href="https://silky.github.io/posts/2019-02-22-2018s-crazy-ideas.html" />
    <id>https://silky.github.io/posts/2019-02-22-2018s-crazy-ideas.html</id>
    <published>2019-02-22T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on February 22, 2019
    
        by Noon van der Silk
    
</div>

<p>I can’t believe I forgot to do this at the start of the year!</p>
<p>Let’s look back over 2018’s ideas:</p>
<h1 id="the-ideas">The Ideas</h1>
<ol>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/470'>using ai to reduce medical dosages</a>: i.e. imagine you need such-and-such amount of radiation in order for certain whatever to be seen in some scan can you lower the dosage and then use some ai technique to enhance the quality of the image?
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/469'>something about shape-based reasoning</a>: i.e. the fact that some grammar-parsing problem teems like a good fit for tensor-network works because they both have the “shape” of a tree another example would be thinking of solving a problem of identifying different types of plants as it fits in the “shape” of a classifier but these things could potentially have <em>other</em> shapes? and therefore fit into <em>other</em> kinds of problems?
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/468'>a q&amp;a bot that can answer tests on the citizenship test</a>: Q: What is our home girt by? A: ..
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/467'>buddhist neural network</a>: it features significant self-attention and self-awareness it performs classification, but predicts the same class for every input as it has a nondual mind it’s loss function features a single term for each of the 6 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/P%C4%81ramit%C4%81">paramitas</a>: - Generosity: to cultivate the attitude of generosity. - Discipline: refraining from harm. - Patience: the ability not to be perturbed by anything. - Diligence: to find joy in what is virtuous, positive or wholesome. - Meditative concentration: not to be distracted. - Wisdom: the perfect discrimination of phenomena, all knowable things.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/466'>music-to-image</a>: say you’re listening to greek music you want to generate an image of a singer singing on some clifftop on greece under an olive tree near a vineyard surely a simple matter of deep learning
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/465'>code story by word frequency</a>: take all the words in a code repo, order them by frequency, then match that up to some standard book, then remap the code according to the frequency
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/464'>generalisation of deutch-jozsa’s problem</a>: here - https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deutsch%E2%80%93Jozsa_algorithm generalise it so that we have multiple f’s that have different promises; i.e. i’m constant “50% of the time”. what now?
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/463'>analogy-lang</a>: reading https://maetl.net/membrane-oriented-programming by <span class="citation" data-cites="maetl">@maetl</span> i had an idea for a programming language consider two types, “person” and “frog”, let’s say there are at least two problems; one is the one in the article - it’s hard to come up with a complete list of methods/properties that should exactly define one of these things. in surfaces and essences they argue that in reality no categorisation has perfectly defined boundaries; so how to define the types? another problem is what happens if i want to build a thing that is both “person-like” and “frog-like”? you can’t. especially not if the differences are far away (i.e. is frog hopping like “walking”? should it be the implementation of a “walk” method? probably not; but a “move” method? probably? but what about less-clear things? and doesn’t it depend on what your merging with) in this way it seems like it’s impossible to come up with strict types for anything so here’s an idea: analogy-lang: let’s you define types in a much more relaxed way; “this thing is like that thing in these ways, but different in these ways”
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/462'>multi-layered network</a>: train some network f to produce y_1 from x_1 f(x_1) = y_1 then, wrap that in a new network, g, that produces y_1 and y_2 from x_1 and x_2 g(x_1, x_2) = ( f(x_1,), g’(x_1, x_2) ) and so on. interesting
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/461'>psychadelics for ai</a>: ideas: - locate some kind of “default-mode network” in your model and inhibit it - after training; allow many more connections - have two modes of network; one this “high-entropy” learning one, which prunes down to a more efficient one that can’t learn but can decide quickly
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/460'>ultimate notification page</a>: it’s just a page with a bunch of iframes to all your different websites where you get the little notification things and then it just tiles them; showing in-which places you have notifications.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/459'>use deep learning to replace a movie character with yourself and your own acting</a>: 1. semantic segmentation to remove an actor 2. film yourself saying their lines 3. plug yourself back into the missing spot 4. dress yourself in the appropriate clothes 5. adjust the lighting 6. ??? 7. profit!
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/458'>paramterised papers</a>: “specifically, this model first generates an aligned position p_t for each target word at time t” show me this sentence with t = whatever and p = some dimension
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/457'>on a slide-deck, have a little small game that plays out in a tiny section of each slide</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/456'>use autocomplete and random phrases to guess things about people</a>: “i love you …” find out who they love “give me …” find out what they want and so on
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/455'>visualise the difference between streaming and shuffling sampling algorithms</a>: streaming -&gt; for low numbers, misses items shuffling -&gt; for low numbers, bad distribution across indices that are shuffled. <span class="citation" data-cites="dseuss">@dseuss</span> <span class="citation" data-cites="martiningram">@martiningram</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/454'>symbolic tensorflow</a>: so i can do convs and explain them really easily
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/453'>the “lentictocular”</a>: uses lenticular technology on a sphere with AI so that it watches your gaze and moves itself accordingly so that it always displays the appropriate time
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/452'>ai email judgement front</a>: intercepts all your emails for every email, it decides the optimal time that someone will respond it sends it at that time so that they respond
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/451'>“growth maps” for determining affected areas of projects w.r.t. a pattern language</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/450'>friend tee</a>: lights up when other friends are nearby
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/449'>lenticular business cards</a>: this is already done by many people
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/448'>innovative holiday inventor</a>: thinks up cool holidays
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/447'>buddhist twitter</a>: there’s only one account, and no password
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/446'>programming ombudsman</a>: <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span> <span class="citation" data-cites="kirillrdy">@kirillrdy</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/445'>the computational complexity of religion</a>: given various religious abilities, what computational problems can you solve? what are the implications on computational complexity by buddhism? and so on.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/444'>spacetime calendar</a>: we have calendars for dates but they don’t often contain space constraints so why not a space-time calendar, defined in some kind of light cone?
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/443'>app to check consistency of items before you leave</a>: it’s an app you configure it to be aware of your keys, laptop, wallet, glasses then, as you leave your house, it can inform you of the status of those items: - “hey, your computer is at home” - “all g, your glasses are at work” etc <span class="citation" data-cites="gacafe">@gacafe</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/442'>gradient tug-of-war demonstration</a>: given a function f(x,y) = x + y then if we have competing loss functions then it would be nice to visualise the gradient flow as a tug of war
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/441'>a website that is entirely defined in the scroll bars/url link bar, whatever</a>: you can move pages by moving your mouse to different parts of the scroll bars and so on in that fashion
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/440'>quantum calendar</a>: it’s a calendar where on any given day in the future, items can be scheduled at the same time. but up to some limit (say 1 week) the items get collapsed and locked in <span class="citation" data-cites="silky">@silky</span> <span class="citation" data-cites="dseuss">@dseuss</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/439'>streaming terminal graph receiving updates over mqtt</a>: then, can use it to plot tensorboard logs to the terminal instead of tensorboard using blessed + blessed-contrib seems to be the easiest way - https://github.com/yaronn/blessed-contrib/blob/master/examples/line-random-colors.js just need to put in the mqtt part and update the data that way.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/438'>ai escape room</a>: this is an idea of dave build an escape room controlled entirely by ai the only way out is by interacting with the machine it can control everything: heating, doors, whatever
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/437'>programmable themepark</a>: here’s a ride; how you interact with it is defined via your own programs you play minigolf, but instead of a club you use programming <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/436'>graph+weights to neuronal net rendering</a>: https://github.com/BlueBrain/NeuroMorphoVis
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/435'>Arbitrary-Task Programming</a>: given that programming is just arranging symbols, <em>and</em> we can use deep learning to interpret the real world into symbols, <em>then</em> it’s possible to do programming by performing arbitrary tasks i.e. <em>any</em> job can be programming, if we can build the deep-learning system that converts actions in that job into symbols in a programming language
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/434'>Sitcom-Lang</a>: it’s a pre-processor, or something, for an arbtrariy language whenever a symbol is defined, that symbol is embued with a soul and a “nature”. it starts to have wants and needs; and those must be satisfied in order for it to stay in it’s present form (i.e. as a “for loop”), otherwise it might change (i.e. to be a “while” loop, or maybe even a string instead). all the symbols will interact with each other, and in that way a program will be made <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/433'>brain2object2teeshirt</a>: this - https://scirate.com/arxiv/1810.02223 - but once it’s decided on the object, it gets rendered on your LED tee-shirt <span class="citation" data-cites="geekscape">@geekscape</span> <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/432'>pix2pix sourcecode2cat</a>: generate pictures of source code convert to pictures of cat instant machine for generating cat pictures from code what cat does your code look like? <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/431'>physical xmonad</a>: use the uarm to be a “physical” xmonad you want to write on some piece of paper? no worries, the uarm will re-arrange your physical desk so that everything is conveniently arranged to do that <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/430'>collaborative painting in the style of christopher alexander</a>: it has 3 parts done by 3 artists i draw the left part; you draw the middle, and it has to interact coherently with whatever i’ve drawn; then another person draws the right side, again, it must interact that’s it.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/429'>lego laptops</a>: laptops that plug together in a lego-like way
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/428'>business version of 30 kids vs 2 professional soccer players</a>: 30 grads vs 2 ceos 30 ceos vs 2 grads etc.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/427'>shops in parks</a>: would make the parks safer/nicer, because people would be in them more could limit the type of shops, and their size, but would be a nice way to build a bit more of a community feeling in them
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/426'>an icon next to your public email address that indicates how many unread emails you have</a>: then people can gauge what will happen if they email you
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/425'>ml for configuring linux</a>: “what file should i look at to change default font sizes?” “how can i set up my new gpu? what settings should i set?”
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/424'>water-t-shirt</a>: the essence of a water-bed, in t-shirt form!
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/423'>deep antiques roadshow</a>: the idea explains itself
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/422'>a being that is by-default inherently abstract, instead of inherently practical like us</a>: for them, being practical would be really hard by default they live at the other end of the abstraction spectrum
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/421'>business card bowl</a>: through all the business cards into a bowl; each day, call them, if they don’t want to do business, throw the card out
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/420'>“live blog”</a>: whenever someone visits your blog, instead of reading articles, they get to open a chat window with you in your terminal then you tell them what you’ve been up to; and they can ask you questions
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/419'>software art</a>: take all the source code; stack them up as if the line count is one slice, that’s the structure
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/418'>t-shirt whiteboard</a>: in essence i.e. you can draw on the t-shirt, and the writing just washes out the next time then you can design whatever you want would this just work?
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/417'>physics simulation + diagrams</a>: would be great to define things such as “two pieces of rope inter-twined”, and then “drop” them, but then let that resulting expression become a haskell diagrams Diagram, so that you can then do diagram stuff with it
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/416'>git version flattener</a>: clone a git repo at every revision, into some folder.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/415'>see-through jacket that is also warm</a>: optionally also magnetic <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/414'>magnetic glass</a>: <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/413'>heated keyboard</a>: keeps your fingers warm
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/412'>run an experiment where monkeys/dogs/whatever are encouraged to learn some kind of programming to solve a task</a>: i.e. a monkey gets 1 food package per day but if learns to program, using the tools provided to it, ( something like a giant physical version of scratch ) then it gets 3 food packages in some sense people have tried this, with them solving problems, but has anyone tried it where the tool they use to solve the problem is general, and can be applied to other areas of their life?
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/411'>tree to code</a>: physical trees 1. order trees by the number of leaves 2. order code by the number of statements train a deeplearning network to map between these things then, trees can write computer programs <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/410'>ethical algorithms testing ground</a>: related to the last two #409 #408 basically, people can sign up to be ethical tester algorithms can join to provide games for people to play how would it work?
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/409'>ethical testers</a>: beta testers game testers ethics testers
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/408'>simulation for ethical machine learning problems</a>: consider the situation: “how do i know if this algorithm X is unethical?” well, instead of waiting for the salespeople to tell you, you could just have it run in a simulated environment and <em><strong>see</strong></em> if it’s unethical by the way that it acts.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/407'>minecraft file browser</a>: walk around your filesystem in 3d
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/406'>ocr clipboard copy and paste</a>: select an image region, send it to some text api thing, get the text back in the clipboard
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/405'>low-powered de-colourisation network</a>: learns to convert colour -&gt; black and white if it doesn’t do a good job, it’ll look awesome
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/404'>physical quine</a>: a robot that can type on the computer and write code that writes the program that writes itself
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/403'>deep learning “do” networks</a>: can you include the “do calculus” into neural networks somehow? to make it do some causal things?
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/402'>plot websites on cesium map, browse the internet that way.</a>: web-world
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/401'>animated colour schemes for vim</a>: the colour scheme rotates as you code
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/400'>a tale of three dickens: the movie</a>: it’s an auto-generated movie from locally-coherent slices instead of the book, we make a movie, where all the scenes in the movie are interspersed based on “local coherence” i.e. from two movies select two people having a conversation with someone named bill or, flick between scenes at the beach <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/399'>revolutionary walls</a>: the floor is fixed; but the walls are a tube you pull on some part of the wall to rotate it <span class="citation" data-cites="tall-josh">@tall-josh</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/398'>activation function composer</a>: or more generally, a function composer 1. what does the graph of <code>relu</code> look like? 2. what about the graph of <code>relu . tanh</code> ? and so on, indefinitely and arbitrarily. some features: - what points should be push through? maybe could add certain kinds of initialisations and ranges - add things like drop-out and whatnot.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/397'>record videos of people doing interviews but have their voice replaced by obama and their image replaced by obama</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/396'>hair cut &amp; deep learning deal with the hair-dresser across the road</a>: sit down for a hair cut, get an hour of deep learning consulting as well
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/395'>live action star wars playing out across many websites in the background of cesium js windows</a>: on my website, a death-star is driving around on it’s way somewhere eventually it reachers your website, and destroy’s it’s logo, or something
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/394'>deep learning tcp or upd</a>: find something inbetween
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/393'>meta-search in google</a>: “i want to see all the alternatives to cloud-ranger” it’s impossible to do this search.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/392'>umbrella-scarf / fresh-scarf</a>: it’s a scarf but also, it has a hood that you can pull up, maybe even a clear hood, that let’s you see out front of it, but keeps you under cover could also keep smoke out of your face
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/391'>meme-net</a>: watch video, extract meme i.e. and the rollsafe guy
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/390'>ultimate computer setup person</a>: someone who just has the worlds best computer set up everything works no data is duplicated whole operating system exists in 1.5 gig; they’ve got 510 gig free no conda/ruby/stack issues
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/389'>codebase -&gt; readme</a>: looks at an entire codebase; learns to predict the readme
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/388'>divangulation theorem for websites</a>: <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span> surfaces can be triangulated websites can be divangulated what are the associated theorems?
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/387'>tasting plates for saas, *aas</a>: instead of just saying “sign up now for 6 months free”; just auto-sign people up for x free things, then let them use it up. easy way to get a billion more dollars for your saas business. <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/386'>self-skating skateboard</a>: it drives down to the skate park; skates around on the pipes, does flips, 180s, griding, whatever. <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span> <span class="citation" data-cites="tall-josh">@tall-josh</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/385'>different password entry forms</a>: 1. any password you type logs you in, but they all take you to a different computer. only your password takes to you yours. “honeypassword” 2. you password consists of the actual letters, but also the timing between the letters <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span> 3. any key you press is irrelevant, all that matters is the spacing; everything is done via morse-code (<span class="citation" data-cites="geekscape">@geekscape</span>)
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/384'>congratulations!!!</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/383'>meeting chaos monkey</a>: every time a meeting is scheduled, a random attendee is replaced by some other random staff member
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/382'>consulto the consulting teddybear</a>: <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span> “that sounds good in theory” “have you tried kan-ban’ing that” “moving forward that sounds good, but right now i think we should be pragmatic”
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/381'>small magnets in fabric that can attach to other magnets so-as to create customisable clothing</a>: just put a diff design on by switching out the magnets i just need some small magnets. jaycar sells them
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/380'>“collaboration card”</a>: some way of listing and engaging with people in various projects you’re interested in
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/379'>nlp self-defending thesis</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/378'>rent factor charged in the city based on how innovative your store is</a>: hairdresser: f = 0.85 funky clothing store: f = 0.6 some weird shop that only sells whatever: 0.2 cafe: 1 or some kind of scheme like so
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/377'>e-fabric</a>: like e-ink, but for fabric
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/376'>clothes that change colour with respect to the magnetic fields that are around it</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/375'>grand designs: of computer programs</a>: follow the development of some kind of app, over a few years. hahahaha would be terrible.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/374'>giant magnet that aligns all the spins of the atoms of objects (people?!) so that they can pass through each other with different polarisations</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/373'>dance-curve net</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/372'>shoes that look like little cars</a>: volvo shoes monster-truck shoes lamboghini shoes fi-car shoes etc.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/371'>augmentation reality glasses that convert what people are saying into words that float in front of you that you can read</a>: so you can “hear” what people say to you when you’re wearing headphones
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/370'>“html/css layout searcher”, like visual image search, but for how to lay things out with flex/css/react/whatever</a>: input: some scribble about how you want your content laid out in boxes: output: the css/html that achieves this. there’s some networks that do this already, where they convert the drawings to code. but maybe that can be augmented by thinking of it like a search across already-existing content?
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/369'>“relax ai” or “mindful story ai”</a>: it makes up nice stories, like “you are walking on the beach, you see a small turtle; you follow the turtle for a swim in the water …” could also use cool accents of people, and make sure the story is consistent with another NLP after the first generative run
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/368'>comedy audience that instead of laughing they just say the things people say when they think something is funny</a>: instead of “ahahaha” audience (in unison): “that’s funny” audience (in unison): “good one” audience (in unison): “great joke”
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/367'>Adversial NLP</a>: a sentence so similar to another sentence as to be humanly-indistinguishable, but makes the AI think it’s something wildly different
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/366'>Inflatable Whiteboard Room</a>: it’s a large room, inflatable like a balloon or whatever, but you can walk into it and use the internals of it as a whiteboard useful for offices
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/365'>Collaborative Password Manager</a>: say i want to make a password for a system you will control, but we both need access to maybe i can have my program generate part of it; you’re program generate part, then combine them both on our independent computers, without the entire password leaving either of them could build this on top of the public keys on github somehow; so i just pick the github user i’m going to share a password with could clearly do this immediately by encrypting it with their public key, or something. but maybe something richer can be done
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/364'>Video Issues</a>: <a href="https://vimeo.com/265518095" class="uri">https://vimeo.com/265518095</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/363'>Faux Project Management Generator Thing</a>: it’s an RNN that generates hundreds of tickets in trello or jira or whatever; with arbitrary due dates makes you feel stressed <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span> could be used for project-management training scenarios
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/362'>quantum cppn</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/361'>AIWS</a>: ai for aws you: “hey, i need to computer with whatever to be up at whichever.com and to have some database, blah blah” aiws: “no worries, that’s set up for you!” alt. “talky-form for AWS” <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/360'>deep haircut mirror</a>: a mirror infront of hair-dressers that lets you look at potential haircuts on your own head
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/359'>train a network to learn when to laugh in response to jokes</a>: deep-audience
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/358'>dance led prompt device</a>: it’s a little led board that sits at the front of a dance thing, like a teleprompter, but for dance it puts out the next dance moves a dance-prompter move-prompter
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/357'>Easter Egg Evangelist for Enterprises (E^4)</a>: A floating employee who embeds on teams to consult on how to best add easter-eggs to the features they build.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/356'>self-driving food truck</a>: <span class="citation" data-cites="martiningram">@martiningram</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/355'>Stabbucks</a>: Starbucks for knives. * https://i.imgur.com/1ZCIQnh.jpg * Order venti, grande, etc knives
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/354'>BrainRank</a>: A leaderboard of brain-shaped logos.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/353'>DeliveryNet</a>: Reads prose with impeccable timing.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/352'>Rant Meetup</a>: Rant about stuff that sucks. * No solutions allowed * Surely james has something to say
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/351'>submit an AI-entry to every large festival in melbourne in a single year</a>: https://whatson.melbourne.vic.gov.au/Whatson/Festivals/Pages/festival_calendar.aspx
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/350'>Stochasm</a>: Metal band that plays random notes. * Easy to swap out band members!
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/349'>Seinfreinds</a>: Have the cast of one sitcom act out an episode of another and see if anyone notices.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/348'>hire a comedian to come along to your meetings</a>: they can provide background entertainment me: “hey nice to meet you, this is my associate jerry seinfeld, let’s get started” jerry: “what’s the deal with peanuts?” …
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/347'>stacked double-coffee-cup holder</a>: it’s just a handle, that holds on to two cups, one above the other useful for carrying multiple cups
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/346'>Auto-generating face detection camouflage</a>: Aka, auto-generating styles from https://cvdazzle.com/
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/345'>use the technology of marina (ShapeTex) to make little movable people in jackets</a>: https://www.linkedin.com/in/marina-toeters-a55a685/
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/344'>“studio gan”</a>: it just makes up every single thing, much like #341 , but in more depth and for everything could use for #343 for example.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/343'>the journey of your parcel</a>: imagine you’re waiting for a parcel from auspost you put on your VR headset and you get a real-time view into it’s life; maybe it’s sitting on a boat, on it’s way here, or it’s in an airplane, or it’s driving etc. you’d get a full HD video-style image of the thing moving, that would be completely imagined by a gan or something.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/342'>menu democracy</a>: buy a coffee, earn 1 voting right to change the menu in some way buy more coffees, proceed in this fashion other food yields you more votes
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/341'>dynamic videos built on the fly to answer standard google queries</a>: i.e “use python requests to do post request” a video could be made on the fly using the celeb-generating stuff of stack-gan, then the voice-simulation stuff of lyrebird or whoever, then the lip-moving stuff, the text-to-speech of wavenet or whatever, and some other random backing scene gans and music production networks it would get the content by reading the first answer it finds on google, in some summarised way. <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/340'>fully-automated fashion design</a>: 1. Fashion-MNIST CPPN - At random, pick a random item of clothing, figure out what it is, and generate a large version. 2. Pick a random (creative-commons) photo from Flickr, train a style transfer network on it. 3. Apply the style transfer to a bunch of different clothing items? To make a theme? 4. Pick a name from an RNN? 5. Upload to PAOM? Run-time should be several hours for one collection? Not so bad.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/339'>remote-controlled magnet</a>: a perfectly spherical magnet that can be rolled around by remote.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/338'>use cppn to generate a 3d landscape by determining the height by the colour</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/337'>lunch formation yaml specification</a>: example: <code>lunch:   - sandwhich:     - bread     - butter     - lettuce     - cucumber     - butter     - bread region: cbd</code> elements are ordered by height on the plate. <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/336'>a tale of 3 dickens</a>: combine: 1. a christmas carol 2. a tale of two cities 3. great expectations in order page-by-page. <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/335'>instead of colouring in the retro-haskell tee with colours, print the source code for the program itself in the previous colour</a>: easy!
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/334'>reverse twospace - use offices for other purposes out of hours</a>: silverpond -&gt; t-shirt business on the weekends
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/333'>dance karaoke</a>: like karaoke, but instead of singing you need to dance uses some pose-recognition thing
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/332'>build a markov chain thing and then run all the words through some “smoothing” operation by way of a word embedding</a>: i.e. somehow pick a few lines within embedding space, and move all of the words closer to those lines maybe something would happen
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/331'>naive nn visualisation</a>: just reshape all the weights to be in the shape of an image, normalise the values, and output it.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/330'>map sentences to “the gist”; just a few words</a>: “an embedding that compresses a piece of text to its core concepts” “like if i can compress an image” “then i should be able to compress a book” “and if i can do that that means that i can also write a compressed book” “and have the neural network write my book” <span class="citation" data-cites="gacafe">@gacafe</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/329'>version number which, in ascii, eventually approaches the source code itself</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/328'>personal world map</a>: it’s one of those scaled world maps, where the scaling is determined by say your gps coordinates over a given year, so that it only enlarges the places you go. <span class="citation" data-cites="mobeets">@mobeets</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/327'>water doughnut</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/326'>Deep-Can-I-Do-Deep-Learning-Here?</a>: it’s a network for which you input a situation and it tells you if you can use deep learning to help.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/325'>haskell type journey challenge</a>: get from package x to package y using only the following types once ….
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/324'>make the 3d wall art that we saw at the house of sonya</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/323'>novels in binder-form so that you can take out small sections of the pages and read them</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/322'>multi-agent learning where the agents also watch each other locally and learn from each other</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/321'>ml for learning the life/centers function from christopher alexander</a>: two pictures which one has more life? alt. something about centers?
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/320'>bureaucratic-net</a>: instead of a network that is really good at explanationing it’s decisions, this network is really bad at it. nothing it says makes sense, or alternatively it’s really long-winded in it’s responses. or maybe it’s always right, but it never has any idea why.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/319'>artistic-arxiv</a>: instead of papers, each day take a random few images from every paper and show that. maybe it’d be cool.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/318'>DeepWiki</a>: on normal wikipedia, humans edit pages about concepts in the form of words on deepwiki AIs edit concepts in the form of embeddings by way of adjusting the vectors (or something) they’d need to think about how to manage edits and revisions and so on. but that’s the general idea. <span class="citation" data-cites="sordina">@sordina</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/317'>secret walls: wear the streets (or: graffiti on a wall of clothes; and wear them)</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/316'>a network that is given the punchline and has to work out the setup</a>: <span class="citation" data-cites="icp-jesus">@icp-jesus</span>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/315'>reverse website or inverse website</a>: normally, you visit a site and see the website and you can view source to see the source what about if you could visit a site and see the source, then view the source to see the site
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/314'>endless pasta hat</a>: has a self-pesto’ing tube that pushed out a long piece of spaghetti that you can munch on.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/313'>in the gan setting, the discriminator isn’t needed when generating, maybe there’s another setting where the discriminator is still useful at the generative stage?</a>
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/312'>a jacket that makes amazon’s automated shopping thing think you’re a packet of chips</a>: or something similar
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/311'>CompromiseApp</a>: two people need to agree on something they both have the app person 1 rates the estimated compromise, on a scale, of person 2 person 2 likewise both people record their own <em>true</em> compromise values then, over time, there’s a bunch of things that can be done, such as comparing predicted compromises, total compromises made, etc.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/310'>DerivativeNet</a>: it watches all seinfield episodes and sees if it can generate curb your enthusiasm episodes it reads all smbc comics and sees if it can generate xkcd ones etc.
</li>
<li>
<a href='https://github.com/silky/ideas/issues/309'>Cap-Gun mechanical keyboard</a>: You pull back a bunch of hammers then as you type it fires the caps.
</li>
</ol>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Designing Functional Clothes with Haskell!</title>
    <link href="https://silky.github.io/posts/2019-01-27-Designing-Functional-Cloths-with-Haskell.html" />
    <id>https://silky.github.io/posts/2019-01-27-Designing-Functional-Cloths-with-Haskell.html</id>
    <published>2019-01-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-01-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on January 27, 2019
    
        by Noon van der Silk
    
</div>

<p>So I gave my talk at the Art-and-Tech miniconf at Linux Conf AU earlier this week.</p>
<p>The video of my talk is here:</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UvkKf8ME564" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<p>Other materials are here:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://vandersilk.github.io">Van der Silk Fashion Website</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/18olpV_GvpLbUR6z043cYIZ0yDVInJDuKN1xWnGQv-5k/edit?usp=sharing">Slides</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UvkKf8ME564">Video on YouTube</a>, or on <a href="https://archive.org/details/lca2019-Designing_functional_clothes_with_Haskell">archive.org</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lobste.rs/s/ggk6oq/designing_functional_clothes_with">Discussion on Lobste.rs</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://maetl.net">Mark</a> for having me at the miniconf!</p>
<h4 id="errata">Errata</h4>
<p>Note that there’s a typo on the types of the <code>somethingFun</code> function that has since been corrected in the slides.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Van der Silk Fashion at Linux Conf 2019 - New Zealand</title>
    <link href="https://silky.github.io/posts/2019-01-04-fashion-design-at-linux-conf-nz.html" />
    <id>https://silky.github.io/posts/2019-01-04-fashion-design-at-linux-conf-nz.html</id>
    <published>2019-01-04T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-01-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on January  4, 2019
    
        by Noon van der Silk
    
</div>

<p>Excitingly, this year I’m going to <a href="https://linux.conf.au/">Linux Conference</a>, and giving a talk at the <a href="https://linux.conf.au/schedule/">Art+Tech MiniConf</a>!</p>
<p>To celebrate, I redesigned the <a href="https://vandersilk.github.io">Van der Silk</a> website:</p>
<center>
<img src="/images/vandersilk-fashion.jpg" width="600" />
</center>
<p>Also, very coincidentally, PAOM re-designed their website for the new year, so it’s much easier to find all my designs: <a href="https://paom.com/search?type=product&amp;q=*noonvandersilk*+tag:public">noonvandersilk on PAOM</a>.</p>
<p>Hope to see you there!</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>2018 Books</title>
    <link href="https://silky.github.io/posts/2019-01-03-2018-books.html" />
    <id>https://silky.github.io/posts/2019-01-03-2018-books.html</id>
    <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on January  3, 2019
    
        by Noon van der Silk
    
</div>

<style type="text/css">
div.book {
 display:        flex;
 flex-direction: row;
 padding:        10px;
}

div.book img { margin-right: 10px; }

div.alt { background: #eaeaea; }
</style>
<p>I’ve seen a few people post the books that they’ve read over the last year; so I thought I’d also get in on the action. Here are the books that I read (or partially read), in no particular order, last year:</p>
<h3 id="non-fiction">Non-Fiction</h3>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/oregon.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/616875.The_Oregon_Experiment">The Oregon Experiment</a></strong> by Christopher W. Alexander, Murray Silverstein, Shlomo Angel, Sara Ishikawa, Denny Abrams</p>
<p>Anyone that knows me, knows that Christopher Alexander is basically my personal Jesus. This book is amazing, to me in it’s demonstration of Alexander’s (and collaborators) standard approach to architecture; i.e building via small local activities in an endless cycle according to a specific and developing pattern language. It also contains very important insights, in my mind, in terms of project management and <a href="/posts/2018-11-09-quick-note-on-budgeting.html">budgeting</a>.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/educated.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35133922-educated">Educated</a></strong> by Tara Westover</p>
<p>I learned about this one from <a href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/Books/Educated">Bill Gates</a>. It’s amazing. I found it really fascinating to read about Tara’s life, and how she understood her upbringing. It makes you think quite a lot about the things you tell yourself to make sense of the situations you’re in.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/darkemu.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/21401526-dark-emu">Dark Emu</a></strong> by Bruce Pascoe</p>
<p>Soon to be (if not already) an Australian classic; it’s very interesting to learn an entirely different history about our country and the Aboriginal people. I found it to be reasonably hard reading because there are some solid descriptions of various items and processes that it would’ve been amazing to have pictures of. In any case, necessary reading.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/candor.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29939161-radical-candor">Radical Candor</a></strong> by Kim Malone Scott</p>
<p>I basically hated this book. I think, on the one hand, it <em>does</em> have useful information in it; but for me it came across too much like standard Silicon Valley propoganda. I do think there is good stuff in here, for leaders that struggle with feedback.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/citiesforpeople.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/8556291-cities-for-people">Cities for People</a></strong> by Jan Gehl</p>
<p>Recommended to me by Ryan, who was working as a Barista at from <a href="https://www.streat.com.au/">Streat</a>, this book is, apparently, a classic of urban planning. It’s amazing. It has a incredibly readable style; with lots of pictures and summaries of each paragraph. Jan has had a lot of impact in designing Melbourne, so it’s really interesting to read this book and see and understand the impact he and his team have had.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/factfulness.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/34890015-factfulness">Factfulness</a></strong> by Hans Rosling, Ola Rosling, Anna Rosling Rönnlund</p>
<p>Quite good. From this book I learned about the website <a href="https://www.gapminder.org/dollar-street/">Dollar Street</a>, which is incredible and well worth a visit. Hans has many questions in the book; almost all of which I answered wrong, much like most of his audience that he’s asked the questions to. I learned a lot about how to think about world-wide progress, and that there are interesting organisations out there doing interesting work. I also learned, much to my surprise, that the World Bank isn’t a bank in the sense that I would’ve assumed; it’s main goal is to end poverty!</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/enlightenment.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35696171-enlightenment-now">Enlightenment Now</a></strong> by Steven Pinker</p>
<p>Not bad. This is the first book of Steven Pinker I’ve read. I’m unlikely to read more, after learning about some sexist views he’s had from <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/8031168-delusions-of-gender">Delusions of Gender</a> (not a book I’ve read yet; but heard thoughts from my partner).</p>
<p>I found this book to be reasonably good, and make some solid arguments for continuing to fight against people that don’t think progress is real. Unfortunately, to paraphrase a joke from the Simposns, Steven seems like the kind of person that can use graphs to prove anything that is even remotely true. It contains too many anecdotes and cherry-picked examples.</p>
<p>I’d recommend Factfulness over this one.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/trees.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/28256439-the-hidden-life-of-trees">The Hidden Life of Trees</a></strong> by Peter Wohlleben</p>
<p>Really great. I’ve always been a bit of a hippie, and am mostly vegetarian, so when my partner found out I’d be reading this one, she started to get a bit concerned that I’d soon not even eat greens! Now, I haven’t quite gone that far, but I do really love the ideas and science in this book; and I think it’s really interesting to think of trees and their root-systems as being some giant entity. The one downside to this book is that it occasionally lacks pictures of the concepts that are being described.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/surfaces.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7711871-surfaces-and-essences">Surfaces and Essences</a></strong> by Douglas R. Hofstadter, Emmanuel Sander</p>
<p>Amazing. Probably not for people feeling a bit impatient. The book goes into many examples of the ideas; and makes a strong argument for the idea that all thinking is based on analogies. I’ve always loved analogies, so I’m naturally a big fan.</p>
<p>As someone presently working in AI, I found this book full of many incredibly interesting and relevant ideas; one of which we discussed <a href="/posts/2018-06-16-when-will-google-translate-be-great.html">previously</a>.</p>
<p>If you’re at all interested in when computers might be able to get to think like humans, definitely have a read!</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/buddhism.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/32895535-why-buddhism-is-true">Why Buddhism is True</a></strong> by Robert Wright</p>
<p>Amazing. Recommended to me by my friend Julia. Probably one of the best books I’ve ever read, really; right up there with Christopher Alexander’s “<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3131171-the-nature-of-order">Nature of Order</a>” and “<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/106728.The_Timeless_Way_of_Building">The Timeless Way of Building</a>”. This book is particularly neat, of course, because it takes a scientific approach to making sense of buddhist ideas. Overall, I find lots of agreement between this book, and the ideas of Christopher Alexander, and Surfaces and Essences.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/inferior.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/31869108-inferior">Inferior</a></strong> by Angela Saini</p>
<p>Pretty interesting. In this book Angela debunks many myths about the supposed biological differences between men and women. This is the first book of this kind that I’ve read; it won’t be the last.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/adam-smith.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20821053-how-adam-smith-can-change-your-life">How Adam Smith Can Change Your Life</a></strong> by Russ Roberts</p>
<p>I read this because my partners dad had it in the house. It’s pretty good; it’s really interesting to see the thoughts from someone from so far back in history. For me, this book resonated with the ideas I read in “Why Buddhism is True”. Worth reading if you happen upon it.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/siddartha.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/11510916-siddartha">Siddartha</a></strong> by Hermann Hesse</p>
<p>I was not a fan of this. Recommended to me by my partner; I found it to be way too “on the nose” about enlightenment. I felt like I was being dragged around to understand certain things, in an obliquely mystical way. Maybe it’s because I read it after I read Why Buddhism is True; which is much more direct and scientific.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/last-lecture.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40611510-the-last-lecture">The Last Lecture</a></strong> by Randy Pausch</p>
<p>Quite good; but quite “American”. If you don’t like too much american-style dreams of success and culture, you might not like this. There’s also the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ji5_MqicxSo">video of the talk that inspired it</a> that is well worth watching.</p>
<p>I watched the video way back in the day; and thought I’d finally read the book. I wasn’t disappointed, but I’m not sure I got much new out of the book that I didn’t get out of the talk. Still, worth grabbing if you got something out of the talk.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/big-picture.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26150770-the-big-picture">The Big Picture</a></strong> by Sean Carroll</p>
<p>Not great. Before I’d read this, I really had thought I liked Sean Carroll. But, this book comes across to me as very arrogant. As someone who’s read way too many popular physics books, it contained a fair amount that wasn’t new to me (but that’s okay), but also a fair amount of just plain arrogance about what is known, where we can expect progress and what areas are accessible to science.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/lost-connections.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/34921573-lost-connections">Lost Connections</a></strong> by Johann Hari</p>
<p>I really enjoyed this. I’ve also suffered (mild, I think) depression, and can really relate to the ideas in this book; namely making connections with people. Probably not the solution for everyone, but interesting reading.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/made-by-humans.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40626257-made-by-humans">Made by Humans</a></strong> by Ellen Broad</p>
<p>Not bad. Fairly introductory thoughts on the topic, but from someone working in policy on this area. Nice to see an Australian view on these issues. Worth reading it you want a broad overview.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/reality.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29767627-reality-is-not-what-it-seems">Reality is Not What it Seems</a></strong> by Carlo Rovelli</p>
<p>This is okay. I get very frustrated these days by books that are implicitly sexist; using language like “when man discovered this”, etc, and this book does that a fair bit. I think I was hoping for this to answer more questions than it did; or to be a bit more detailed. I think I probably just misjudged the intended audience.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/brain-time.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35187183-your-brain-is-a-time-machine">Your Brain Is a Time Machine</a></strong> by Dean Buonomano</p>
<p>Pretty good. I haven’t read much about neuroscience, and I am really mostly confused about the physics of time, and problems like the so-called “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arrow_of_time">arrow of time</a>”, and such. So I found this to be pretty interesting, and have some good ideas in it that I hadn’t thought about, such as different “clocks” in the body for different purposes.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<p><img src="/images/books-2018/i-feel-you.jpg" /></p>
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36808161-i-feel-you">I Feel You</a></strong> by Cris Beam</p>
<p>Interesting, but odd. I found this book to be worthwhile reading; in particular because it lead me to some interesting ideas around the <a href="/posts/2018-07-25-ethics-of-AI.html">ethics of AI</a>. Cris goes into weird details of empathy in use in businesses, and life. Overall, worth taking a look at.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<p><img src="/images/books-2018/psychadelics.jpg" /></p>
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36613747-how-to-change-your-mind">How to Change Your Mind</a></strong> by Michael Pollan</p>
<p>Great. Never having taken psychadelics myself, and basically having the view that they are a bit dangerous, this book totally changed my mind. I found it totally fascinating, alongside Why Buddhism is True, in terms of a potential path towards enlightenment. It’s certainly interesting to learn about the history of psychadelic drugs, and think about the connection to mindful meditation.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/nature-of-order.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3131171-the-nature-of-order">The Nature of Order - Book 1 - The Phenomenon of Life</a></strong> by Christopher Alexander</p>
<p>Incredible. As we learned at the start, Christopher Alexander is my personal Jesus and this set of books is essentially his bible. As a result, this is amazing reading for me. He describes what it means for something to “have life”; he goes into detail by way of examples, a mathematical model, and a practical, hands-on theory. He breaks it down into what he refers to as “centers”; things that build on each other.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/value.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29502362-the-value-of-everything">The Value of Everything</a></strong> by Mariana Mazzucato</p>
<p>Amazing. I’m only part of the way through this book, but I love it. We saw Mariana talk at some event a few weeks ago; and she’s an amazing speaker with a incredibly ability to talk with enthusiasm about complicated ideas.</p>
<p>This book is all about “value” vs “price”; and what industries should be considered “productive” in how they contributed to the economoy. In particular it’s really opened my eyes about the finance industry. Amazing reading.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<p><img src="/images/books-2018/how-to-sit.jpg" /></p>
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18342486-how-to-sit">How To Sit</a></strong>, <strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22928976-how-to-walk">How To Walk</a></strong> by Thich Nhat Hanh</p>
<p>Amazing, and useful. I’ve found these two (small) books really good to read when I’m feeling stressed or overwhelmed. They contain many little thoughts that help ground and relax you.</p>
</div>
</div>
<h3 id="fiction">Fiction</h3>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/the-power.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29751398-the-power">The Power</a></strong> by Naomi Alderman</p>
<p>Pretty good. Best read without too much knowledge of what it’s about. Worth reading.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/the-martian.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18007564-the-martian">The Martian</a></strong> by Andy Weir</p>
<p>Awesome. Instant classic. Great fun.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/all-the-birds.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25372801-all-the-birds-in-the-sky">All the Birds in the Sky</a></strong> by Charlie Jane Anders</p>
<p>Pretty fun. A nice and simple read. I enjoyed it.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/fifth-season.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p>The Broken Earth Series: <strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/19161852-the-fifth-season">The Fifth Season</a></strong>, <strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26228034-the-obelisk-gate">The Obselisk Gate</a></strong>, <strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/31817749-the-stone-sky">The Stone Sky</a></strong>, by N. K. Jemisin</p>
<p>Incredible. The first series of books I read by N. K. Jemisin. I couldn’t put these down, and as soon as I’d finished the first one I bought the remaining two and couldn’t wait to read them.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/inheritance.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/21481566-the-inheritance-trilogy">The Inheritance Trilogy</a></strong> by N. K. Jemisin</p>
<p>Really great. N. K. Jemisin is easily my favourite Sci-Fi author at the moment and I’ll probably read anything she writes. So interesting, unique, and innovative.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/dreamblood.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29775367-the-dreamblood-duology">The Dreamblood Duology</a></strong> by N. K. Jemisin</p>
<p>Really great. Quite different, really, from The Inheritance Trilogy, but still amazing.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/less.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/39927096-less">Less</a></strong> by Andrew Sean Greer</p>
<p>Not bad. I picked it up off the table in the bookshop because it had won the Pulitzer Prize, and I figured it might be good. I found it to be pretty good; but utlimately not quite my style.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="book alt">
<div class="img">
<img src="/images/books-2018/kings.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="text">
<p>The Stormlight Archive <strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7235533-the-way-of-kings">The Way of Kings</a></strong>, <strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17332218-words-of-radiance">Words of Radiance</a></strong>, <strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/34002132-oathbringer">Oathbringer</a></strong>, by Brandon Sanderson</p>
<p>Awesome. I discovered Brandon after looking for something new after finishing <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/series/41526-the-wheel-of-time">The Wheel of Time</a>. I’m really enjoying this series, and can’t wait for the next one!</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Hope you enjoyed this list! If you have any suggestions of books, I’d be really interested!</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Reliable training hack on the Google Colaboratory</title>
    <link href="https://silky.github.io/posts/2018-11-19-reliable-training-hack-on-google-colaboratory.html" />
    <id>https://silky.github.io/posts/2018-11-19-reliable-training-hack-on-google-colaboratory.html</id>
    <published>2018-11-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on November 19, 2018
    
        by Noon van der Silk
    
</div>

<p>Google’s <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/notebooks/welcome.ipynb#recent=true">Colaboratory</a> is a hosted notebook environment, with access to GPUs, and even TPUs!</p>
<p>It’s really quite handy, but by far the biggest downside is that the sessions time out. It makes sense; I’m sure even Google can’t give out an unlimited amount of compute-resources for free to every person.</p>
<h3 id="backgroundproblem">Background/Problem</h3>
<p>On the weekend, I wanted to train a few <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/magenta/tree/master/magenta/models/sketch_rnn">sketch-rnn models</a> on the <a href="https://quickdraw.withgoogle.com/data">quickdraw data</a>.</p>
<p>Naively, I figured this would be really easy with Google colab. While it was straightforward to start training, what I noticed is that getting data on to and off of the instance was frustrating, and the timeouts blocked me from getting a good amount of training time.</p>
<h3 id="solution">Solution</h3>
<p>Happily, colab supports very nice integration with Google services, so my plan was:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Download data from Google Cloud Platform (GCP),</li>
<li>Train, or continue training,</li>
<li>Push a checkpoint to Google Drive occasionally,</li>
<li>Repeat until happy.</li>
</ol>
<p>Here’s how it looks, in code:</p>
<p><strong>Download data from GCP</strong></p>
<p>As I’m working with the quickdraw data, it’s already on the Google Cloud Platform, so this was very easy. In a cell, I simply ran the following to get the “eye” quickdraw data:</p>
<pre><code>!gsutil cp gs://quickdraw_dataset/sketchrnn/eye.npz .</code></pre>
<p>(Note that the <code>gsutil</code> command is already installed on the instance.)</p>
<p><strong>Train, or continue training, and save to Drive</strong></p>
<p>As I’m using the <code>sketch_rnn</code> model, I first simply install <code>magenta</code> (and I have to pick a Python 2 environment.)</p>
<pre><code>!pip install magenta</code></pre>
<p>Now, there’s some considerations. Recalling that I’m going to be pushing my checkpoints to Google Drive, I need to authenticate with Google Drive. This is how that looks:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb3"><pre class="sourceCode python"><code class="sourceCode python"><a class="sourceLine" id="cb3-1" title="1"><span class="im">from</span> google.colab <span class="im">import</span> auth</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb3-2" title="2">auth.authenticate_user()</a></code></pre></div>
<p>Then you’ll be prompted to copy in a code. Once that’s done, you can connect to Google Drive like so:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb4"><pre class="sourceCode python"><code class="sourceCode python"><a class="sourceLine" id="cb4-1" title="1"><span class="im">from</span> googleapiclient.discovery <span class="im">import</span> build</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb4-2" title="2">drive_service <span class="op">=</span> build(<span class="st">&#39;drive&#39;</span>, <span class="st">&#39;v3&#39;</span>)</a></code></pre></div>
<p>Now, if I’m training from scratch, I’ll run something like this:</p>
<pre><code>!sketch_rnn_train --log_root=logs --data_dir=./ --hparams=&quot;data_set=[eye.npz],num_steps=501&quot;</code></pre>
<p>This will run for however long, and utlimately produce checkpoints in the <code>./logs</code> folder, supposing that <code>eye.npz</code> exists in the present directory.</p>
<p>Once that’s completed, I start my main training-pushing loop. Firstly, there’s a bit of busywork to zip files, get the latest checkpoint number, and upload it to Google Drive:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb6"><pre class="sourceCode python"><code class="sourceCode python"><a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-1" title="1"><span class="im">import</span> os</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-2" title="2"><span class="im">import</span> zipfile</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-3" title="3"><span class="im">from</span> googleapiclient.http <span class="im">import</span> MediaFileUpload</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-4" title="4"></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-5" title="5"><span class="kw">def</span> get_largest_num (<span class="bu">dir</span><span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;logs&quot;</span>, prefix<span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;vector&quot;</span>):</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-6" title="6">  </a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-7" title="7">  files <span class="op">=</span> os.listdir(<span class="bu">dir</span>)</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-8" title="8">  </a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-9" title="9">  biggest <span class="op">=</span> <span class="dv">0</span></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-10" title="10">  </a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-11" title="11">  <span class="cf">for</span> f <span class="kw">in</span> files:</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-12" title="12">    <span class="cf">if</span> f.startswith(prefix):</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-13" title="13">      k <span class="op">=</span> <span class="bu">int</span>( f.split(<span class="st">&quot;.&quot;</span>)[<span class="dv">0</span>].split(<span class="st">&quot;-&quot;</span>)[<span class="dv">1</span>] ) </a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-14" title="14">      <span class="cf">if</span> k <span class="op">&gt;</span> biggest:</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-15" title="15">        biggest <span class="op">=</span> k</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-16" title="16">  </a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-17" title="17">  <span class="cf">return</span> biggest</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-18" title="18"></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-19" title="19"></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-20" title="20"><span class="kw">def</span> zip_model (name, k):</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-21" title="21">  sk     <span class="op">=</span> <span class="bu">str</span>(k)</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-22" title="22">  zipobj <span class="op">=</span> zipfile.ZipFile(name <span class="op">+</span> <span class="st">&quot;.zip&quot;</span>, <span class="st">&quot;w&quot;</span>, zipfile.ZIP_DEFLATED)</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-23" title="23"></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-24" title="24">  files <span class="op">=</span> [ <span class="st">&quot;checkpoint&quot;</span></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-25" title="25">          , <span class="st">&quot;model_config.json&quot;</span></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-26" title="26">          , <span class="st">&quot;vector-&quot;</span> <span class="op">+</span> sk <span class="op">+</span> <span class="st">&quot;.meta&quot;</span></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-27" title="27">          , <span class="st">&quot;vector-&quot;</span> <span class="op">+</span> sk <span class="op">+</span> <span class="st">&quot;.index&quot;</span></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-28" title="28">          , <span class="st">&quot;vector-&quot;</span> <span class="op">+</span> sk <span class="op">+</span> <span class="st">&quot;.data-00000-of-00001&quot;</span>]</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-29" title="29">  </a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-30" title="30">  <span class="cf">for</span> f <span class="kw">in</span> files:</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-31" title="31">    zipobj.write(<span class="st">&quot;logs/&quot;</span> <span class="op">+</span> f, f)</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-32" title="32"></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-33" title="33"></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-34" title="34"></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-35" title="35"><span class="kw">def</span> upload_to_drive (name<span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;model.zip&quot;</span>):</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-36" title="36">  file_metadata <span class="op">=</span> {</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-37" title="37">    <span class="st">&quot;name&quot;</span>:     name,</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-38" title="38">    <span class="st">&quot;mimeType&quot;</span>: <span class="st">&quot;binary/octet-stream&quot;</span> }</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-39" title="39"></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-40" title="40">  media <span class="op">=</span> MediaFileUpload(name, </a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-41" title="41">                          mimetype<span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;binary/octet-stream&quot;</span>,</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-42" title="42">                          resumable<span class="op">=</span><span class="va">True</span>)</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-43" title="43"></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-44" title="44">  created <span class="op">=</span> drive_service.files().create(body<span class="op">=</span>file_metadata,</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-45" title="45">                                         media_body<span class="op">=</span>media,</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-46" title="46">                                         fields<span class="op">=</span><span class="st">&quot;id&quot;</span>).execute()</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-47" title="47">  file_id <span class="op">=</span> created.get(<span class="st">&quot;id&quot;</span>)</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb6-48" title="48">  <span class="cf">return</span> file_id</a></code></pre></div>
<p>Then, the main loop:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb7"><pre class="sourceCode python"><code class="sourceCode python"><a class="sourceLine" id="cb7-1" title="1">iterations <span class="op">=</span> <span class="dv">200</span></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb7-2" title="2"><span class="cf">for</span> k <span class="kw">in</span> <span class="bu">range</span>(iterations):</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb7-3" title="3">  <span class="bu">print</span>(<span class="st">&quot;Iteration &quot;</span> <span class="op">+</span> <span class="bu">str</span>(k))</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb7-4" title="4">  cmd <span class="op">=</span> <span class="st">&#39;sketch_rnn_train --log_root=logs --resume_training --data_dir=./ &#39;</span> <span class="op">+</span> <span class="op">\</span></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb7-5" title="5">        <span class="co">&#39; --hparams=&quot;data_set=[eye.npz],num_steps=1001&quot;&#39;</span></a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb7-6" title="6">  x <span class="op">=</span> os.system(cmd)</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb7-7" title="7">  zip_model(<span class="st">&quot;model&quot;</span>, get_largest_num())</a>
<a class="sourceLine" id="cb7-8" title="8">  upload_to_drive()</a></code></pre></div>
<p>So, all that does is run the main training command, to reload the model from the latest checkpoint and continue training, then zips and uploads!</p>
<p>Set the iterations to whatever you wish; chances are your instance will never run for that long anyway; the main point is to push up the checkpoints every-so-often (for me, every 1000 steps of the sketch_rnn model; which takes about 1 hour or so, depending on params.)</p>
<p><strong>Brining down the most recent Drive checkpoint</strong></p>
<p>Now, when your instance goes away, you’ll need to bring down the most recent checkpoint <em>from</em> Drive. I did this somewhat manually, but it works well enough:</p>
<pre><code># Mount Google Drive as a folder
from google.colab import drive
drive.mount(&#39;/content/gdrive&#39;)</code></pre>
<pre><code># Extract latest model zip file
!cp /content/gdrive/My\ Drive/model\ \(3\).zip logs/model.zip &amp;&amp; cd logs &amp;&amp; unzip model.zip</code></pre>
<p>Note that Google Drive numbers all the files as copies, like “model (4).zip”, “model (5).zip”, when you upload the same name. On the web interface, it only shows one file, but gives you history. Do as you wish here; I was a bit lazy.</p>
<h3 id="thats-it">That’s it!</h3>
<p>Hope this helps you do some training!</p>
<p>You can read more about other ways to access data from Google Colaboratory <a href="https://colab.research.google.com/notebooks/io.ipynb">here</a>.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>A quick note on budgeting ...</title>
    <link href="https://silky.github.io/posts/2018-11-09-quick-note-on-budgeting.html" />
    <id>https://silky.github.io/posts/2018-11-09-quick-note-on-budgeting.html</id>
    <published>2018-11-09T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="info">
    Posted on November  9, 2018
    
        by Noon van der Silk
    
</div>

<p>In “<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/616875.The_Oregon_Experiment">The Oregon Experiment</a>”, the authors consider the following budgeting scenario.</p>
<p>Suppose you’re in the following situation: You have ~$2,500,000 that you’d like to allocate to construction projects in your community.</p>
<p>There are many ways you can allocate this money to projects of varying sizes. Consider the following options:</p>
<style type="text/css">
table.budget {
margin: 10px;
background: #eaeaea;
}
table.budget th {
border: 0;
margin: 0;
border-bottom: solid 1px gray;
}
table.budget td {
border: 0;
padding: 5px;
}
table.budget td.r {
text-align: right;
}
td.m, th.m { width: 100px; }
td.r, th.r { width: 150px; }
table.budget td.m {
text-align: center;
}
table.budget tr.total td {
border-top: solid 1px gray;
}
div.tables {
display: flex;
flex-direction: row;
flex-wrap: wrap;
justify-content: center;
}
div.tables div {
display: flex;
flex-direction: column;
}
</style>
<div class="tables">
<div>
<h3 id="option-1---all-projects-considered-equally">Option 1 - All projects considered equally</h3>
<table class="budget">
<tr>
<th>
category
</th>
<th class="m">
number of projects
</th>
<th class="r">
rough total cost based on averages
</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
A &lt; $1000
</td>
<td class="m">
1
</td>
<td class="r">
$500
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
B $1000-$10,000
</td>
<td class="m">
1
</td>
<td class="r">
$5,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
C $10,000-$100,000
</td>
<td class="m">
1
</td>
<td class="r">
$50,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
D $100,000-$1,000,000
</td>
<td class="m">
1
</td>
<td class="r">
$500,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
E &gt; $1,000,000
</td>
<td class="m">
1
</td>
<td class="r">
$2,000,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="total">
<td>
<b>totals</b>
</td>
<td class="m">
5
</td>
<td class="r">
~$2,600,000
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</div>
<div>
<h3 id="option-2---projects-considered-unequally">Option 2 - Projects considered unequally</h3>
<table class="budget">
<tr>
<th>
category
</th>
<th class="m">
number of projects
</th>
<th class="r">
rough total cost based on averages
</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
A &lt; $1000
</td>
<td class="m">
1000
</td>
<td class="r">
$500,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
B $1000-$10,000
</td>
<td class="m">
100
</td>
<td class="r">
$500,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
C $10,000-$100,000
</td>
<td class="m">
10
</td>
<td class="r">
$500,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
D $100,000-$1,000,000
</td>
<td class="m">
1
</td>
<td class="r">
$500,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
E &gt; $1,000,000
</td>
<td class="m">
⅒ th of a project
</td>
<td class="r">
$500,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="total">
<td>
<b>totals</b>
</td>
<td class="m">
~1100
</td>
<td class="r">
$2,500,000
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</div>
<div>
<h3 id="option-3---a-middle-ground">Option 3 - A middle ground</h3>
<table class="budget">
<tr>
<th>
category
</th>
<th class="m">
number of projects
</th>
<th class="r">
rough total cost based on averages
</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
A &lt; $1000
</td>
<td class="m">
500
</td>
<td class="r">
$250,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
B $1000-$10,000
</td>
<td class="m">
50
</td>
<td class="r">
$250,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
C $10,000-$100,000
</td>
<td class="m">
10
</td>
<td class="r">
$500,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
D $100,000-$1,000,000
</td>
<td class="m">
1
</td>
<td class="r">
$500,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
E &gt; $1,000,000
</td>
<td class="m">
1
</td>
<td class="r">
$1,000,000
</td>
</tr>
<tr class="total">
<td>
<b>totals</b>
</td>
<td class="m">
~550
</td>
<td class="r">
$2,500,000
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</div>
</div>
<p>The main conclusion is that, for the same amount of money, we can chose to either support lots of small projects, or few total projects.</p>
<p>One of the main premises of the book, is that good change is made locally, by locals. In this way, schemes 2 and 3 are a <em>significant</em> improvement over Option 1.</p>
<p>One of the best initiatives that Victoria is doing along these lines is the “<a href="https://pickmyproject.vic.gov.au/">Pick My Project</a>” program.</p>
<p>However, I think it’s also interesting to think about this in relation to other areas:</p>
<ul>
<li>Health: Should you make one big change? Or many small ones?</li>
<li>Programming: Should you write one big program? Or many little ones?</li>
<li>Management: Should you set big goals from the top? Or should you empower the people below you to set their own goals?</li>
</ul>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
